[Music]
great to see you in in reality rather
than as a face as a internet avatar your
thoughts have been in mine or your voice
has been in my head for the past yeah
it's a pleasure to meet you I don't even
you saw but I uh I tweeted about the
what you wrote yes thank you very much
for yeah I thought excellent I thought
it was some excellent work excellent
commentary excellent critique really
well done deeply appreciative of that
kind of engagement thank you thank you
very much yeah thank you yeah I think
the reason I write these what I mean one
of my motivations besides the fact that
I love them is is that it's it's high
abstract stuff and and so I always have
to go through your your videos a couple
times to get it and so if I write about
it you know I'll absorb it I'll be able
to you know keep it with me whereas if I
just listen to it like well I'm washing
the dishes or something like that it'll
just like water going through my brain
you know a lot of the essential concepts
well I'm glad I mean that's yeah that's
the elaborative strategy and that that
is the way to deeply understand
something is to try and I can have a
generative response to it where you
actually write about a wrestle with it
that's why I deeply appreciate when
people have watch parties about the park
the parking and discussing the church oh
yeah if you guys yeah yeah that's if I
had if I you know that's how I would
prefer at I prefer that videos would be
watched then they're not just watched
they like you say with somebody riding
their bicycle just listening to me in a
monologic fashion but if they got and
I've got to attend one of those there's
a there's a city near me Kingston I'm in
Toronto it's about two and a half hours
away by drive and they're in a movie
theater they're showing the video series
alright yeah yeah and so and so I got to
actually go out there and participate
with like
you know you know watching with these
people and then doing discussion and
live Q&A with them that was just such a
wonderful experience that that is that
is really how I would like the videos to
be to be watched because yeah they're
not they're not intended to be monologic
I mean obviously I have to present them
that way because I'm by myself but yeah
very very much what you're doing is to
deeply appreciate it deeply appreciate
it thank you and it's it's what you're
doing is I I appreciate very much on the
level that you are a university
professor but you're also reaching out
to talk to the people in a sense every
way that makes a so it seems to me like
there's there's this two worlds right
there's academia and then there's this
other kind of world and they seem kind
of separate and you're bridging those
two worlds yeah very much so that's very
much what I'm trying to do I I'm very
much I I think that I want I don't want
to be I don't want to be just
disrespectful to my academic home
because the University of Toronto treats
me extremely well and I'm deeply
appreciative for that so take that into
consideration when I say I don't think
the academic world is going to be the
place where we're where we come up with
the solutions to the meeting crisis
I think academic work has a role in that
but it is not going to be the locus
where where the the response to the
meeting crisis is going to be found so
bridging this stuff out and getting the
kind of stuff that's happening right now
between you and I that's the place where
it's going to happen and and so that was
that was the intent of the work that I
tried to do it was motivated by that
deep belief that with the academic world
it's too insulated um and and and and to
sort of spun up in just propositional
exchange I'm for doing what's needed to
be to need what needs to be done yeah
there's almost even though this is
online stuff it's almost more like I
almost feel like myself I haven't been
an academic for a long
I mean I haven't never really been in
academic but it's almost like a street
kind of writing yeah less than an
academic kind of writing what I what I'm
doing like I think I'm so I'm
translating stuff that you're doing in a
sense in a way that I can understand it
to communicate to people and this is
kind of making me a student again so I'm
kind of going back into the academia and
I'm like taking notes and and so it's
sort of extending I think for a lot of
people also extending our learning
process you know outside of the confines
of yeah that's never enough ELISA love
learning there there are right that's
that's what someone woman when I went to
this this this meet up the watch party
in Kingston
she actually said yeah thank you for
bringing the university to us and bring
an exact learnings back to us and so I'm
glad you I'd you feel that because
that's actually one of the goals I want
to try to do with my work I have a list
of questions for you one of the big ones
I have is this question about what is a
religion that is not a religion yeah and
the reason it's kind of an important
question to me is because I've been a
practicing Buddhist in a formal sense
since my twins so so I I kind of at one
point decided okay you know and I've
there's been times where I I haven't
really liked the label and I wouldn't
want to identify myself with that and
other times where I thought it was
important to do that so I've fluctuated
between in my life between filling up
that I am a formal Buddhist and not a
Buddhist so anyway I want to you know
just get your view on on on that whole
thing and and and my fear is a religion
that's not a religion is is sort of
still a religion or yeah I mean
obviously I there's a sense in which I'm
deliberately and explicitly who's using
a contradictory statement I'm trying to
I'm trying to be a gauging what I call
serious playwright I'm trying to be
provocative rather than give a
definitive declaration to things I want
to do I just wanted to again I wanted to
thank you for all the commentary and
excellent critique you do of my work
it's been it's really good and I also
wanted to let you know that the earlier
this morning I was just actually talking
to Jordan Hall explicitly about this
question we were doing some further work
on it he gave me permission to mention
any of the ideas that we talked about
there so let me try and answer that
question again with the understanding
that you know this is in conversation
with Chris master Pho Dean conversation
with Jordan Hall it's very important for
me to people always know the the
collaborative cohort that you know that
I'm working with yeah and so I just I
just want to make that clear to your
viewers so one of the things I want one
of the things I'm trying to say is first
of all the part of it emerged out of a
problem that I see a problem that I see
is the following and I have arguments
for each point that I want to make so if
you want to go back and unpack any point
any one point I'm gonna make
argumentatively I'm prepared to do that
but I'm gonna try and answer your
question more schematically overarching
right now I think something like religio
for reasons i articulate is is it
inevitable to human beings this sense of
you know a participatory connectedness
to ourselves to each other to the world
that there isn't just that isn't just
propositional it's deeply embodied it's
deeply enacted and that and that we need
to not only have that happening we need
to we need to be able to how do I want
to put we need to be able to reliably
activate it celebrate it accentuate it
develop it there's a it has a
developmental aspirational Drive to it
and we get a kind of deep existential
and motivational even emotional reward
from engaging with and celebrating or
religio in that sense it's inevitable to
us because I think it's so central to
our cognitive agency so we need
and I mean you've seen this series you
know there's a long argument for this in
terms of relevance realization etc so
I'm gonna take that as a premise for
what I'm not going to say so we need
something we need a set you know we need
sets of practices you know ecologies of
psycho technologies as I put it for
doing that for activating and
accentuating and aspirating our religio
in reliable developmental ways a problem
well I just want to stop and say that
the the question I have then is why do
we not keep the the actual traditions we
have and reformed them rather than just
start from scratch it isn't there a
danger there in assertive language later
kind of ideology yeah totally totally
and and so I'll just both of those so
that's it the next point is exactly
where it's a perfect segue so thank you
so what's the problematic about that
well the problematic I see for that and
and and there's I think demographic
evidence to support this with the rise
of the nuns and and all and the rise of
sort of pervasive background culturally
accepted sort of nihilism and cynicism
is that the traditional religious forms
are not working for many people and I
think part of that this is not meant to
be an exhaustive explanation but I think
part of that is the psycho technologies
we can't we can't get we can't get rid
we can't unlearn a lot of the cyclic
technologies and practices like and the
way they've transformed our
consciousness and cognition but what
many people can no longer adhere to and
I playing with under most believe and
connect to like what they can no longer
its adhere to is the axial age to
world's mythology that sort of
legitimated and valorized
and provided institutions and guides for
this for most people oh great I have
another question for you if I can jump
in again jump into this you don't mind
related to that so you know I I said you
know I'm sort of in a sense
ask the question about tradition yeah
but also um in another way I'm very
sympathetic to you because whenever I
talk to Christians they seem to think
that their way is the only way and it
seems almost all pervasive with with
Christians and it's probably the same
with people who are Islamic or are most
of the major you know it's not everybody
but but and also that there is an
orthodox way of doing things and there's
absolutely there's there's no sort of
boundaries between those no possibility
for a Christian to meditate or you know
or or or or you know does that is that
so that that's are you feeling my sort
of struggle with all this or why am i I
want to let me reply to that and then
also finished the point is making you
know trying to keep the nesting clear
for people I I definitely have met those
people as you may know I grew up in a
fundamentalist Christian family
background and so I'm very I know very
deeply from the inside what you're
talking about
of course I've met Christians who are
much more open and exploratory than I
get into excellent conversation here I'm
sure I should I should also point out
that I have met in deep conversation
even Buddhists who also come to that
play that this is ultimately the only
way right right I need you though agree
yeah yeah so I don't I don't want to pin
this to any one particular religion I
find this as a as a sort of perennial
problem with the religions so if if we
agree that there's that sort of
institutional sort of constraint I think
there's also an epistemic constraint in
that the the two worlds view and there's
we there's all kinds of axial variations
on it it can be heaven and earth it
could be nirvana samsara it could be the
promised land and Egypt like there's all
kinds of mythological representations of
this and and the variation is part of
why that that mythology was precisely so
powerfully successful is it was it was
capable of a kind of evolution that game
it sustaining presence
but nevertheless that to world's grammar
right is largely and for again I have an
argument out there for this I'm just yes
it's largely deeply incompatible with
the scientific worldview and then and
and you have to do more with the
scientific it's a scientific worldview
not just science right and then this is
a Haida garyun point it has permeated
our cultural grammar it is it surrounds
us with the tech without with our
technology right people who say well I
reject the scientific worldview while
they're using all of this technology and
moving around and using all these psycho
technologies like graphing and you know
and mathematical like mathematical
equations for understanding reality this
is heidegger's point right it is deep it
is it is soaked deep deep into us the
scientific world right is it is a
scientific worldview incompatible with
the traditional religious worldview is
that no that's it now that's a better
question where I and the way I posed it
what I want to say is and this overlaps
with your point about a kind of
conservatism in the institutions if the
religious tradition is identified with
that axial age to world grammar I think
that renders it incapable of
reconciliation ok scientific worldview
that's great now and I think that and I
think you can see traditions of
Orthodoxy that have basically made that
identification sacrosanct now I want to
step back and be fair there are lots of
Christians are I'm talking to publicly
like right now Mary Coe and Paul van der
clay JP what more so right who are
willing to pull those apart and say yes
we want to try it we want to somehow
change the ontology of Christianity and
get it free from the axial age so again
I want to be fair but what I'm saying is
in general for most people looking at
the traditions and I think with a fair
degree of legitimacy they are being told
from within these traditions that that
Axial Age mythology and the religious
tradition are deeply identifiable
together that's the kind of or that
see and I think as long as that
identification is in place and I mean
there's also remote ISM - yeah I think
you can that's why I know you're right -
to bring that back to Buddhism and for
me not to just say that it's you know
not to pick on Christianity it's it's
definitely the case that there's
fundamentalist Buddhists yeah maybe I've
been one at one point yeah yeah and
totally and it's and so like this is why
you you see people and I you know I've
met I've met I've met even Bachelor and
Evan Thompson is a good friend of mine
if Steven Bachelor has written after
Buddhism Evan Thompson is written why
I'm not a Buddhist for precisely these
kinds of arguments so these are deeply
thoughtful academic people who have
wrestled with trying to reconcile for
example Buddhism with the scientific
worldview and finding so much resistance
again about a commitment to the actual
Age of Mythology that they finally felt
that they had to abandon the
relationship to Buddhism so well again
that's that's part of my argument that's
part of my argument sure
III I've also met people who are let's
say who take on the traditional Buddhist
thing 100% and find absolutely zero
problem with you know a scientific
worldview and also you know in the
tantric traditions that then I practice
there's there's all kinds of things that
are done that are really I guess trans
rational or not the least fit
compatibility with with rationality so I
guess that ties in to my second question
really that I had here about rationality
so maybe we can drink you can bring
those two to thought to finish one point
in that the point about the the reason
why it's also the religion that's not a
religion is also it's it's kind of
bookended it's a for the argument I
tried to articulate many people find
they attempt to go into the traditions
non-viable for them and I mean that in
the sense that James met like you didn't
you can see it's not a livable
proposition for them and I think the the
what people perceive that's why it's not
a religion but why is it a religion if
you'll allow me the contradiction
because the secular alternatives
the pseudo religious ideologies right
the the the you know that that direct
like you pointed out in the commentary
that drenched the world and blood those
secular although that I don't think that
ultimately they were purely secular but
they styled themselves as nearly secular
alternative purely political that is no
that I think that option is also you
know blocked for most people that's not
an option so people feel trapped you
know that no I can't go back to religion
but that secular alternatives don't work
too and I was trying to capture that
tension with with the contradiction like
it's not a religion for the people who I
can't go back to the tradition but it's
still a religion in the acknowledgment
well the second or alternatives don't
work either that's what I was trying to
capture with that trying to capture the
tension with with with that and the
problematic that it gives us huh well
what do you think for example of a deity
yoga practice where you visualize
yourself as some kind of wild deity you
know in union with you know there's this
kind of very very bizarre practices
which are just I think that the modern
rational person you know they're
effective and they're beautiful but IIIi
don't think I can apply rationality to
them where I don't think I could apply
like maybe I could but what let's talk
about that I want to talk about that
excellent that's an excellent question
because as you know I I'm not just me
many people and I try to reference them
are doing we're trying to I think get
back to at least an ancient Greek notion
of rationality as opposed to a very
Cartesian rationality and I think that
is what we need because we need a notion
of rationality that connects us back to
wisdom and so let's let's take it for
granted that that's you know that that's
a reasonable proposal again I've got
arguments out there for that but let's
say that what we're interested in is a
notion of rationality as it was in the
ancient world bit of
Ford's right some understanding bridges
to the cultivation of wisdom well then
and this is so pervasive through you
know ancient philosophy ax the notion of
rationality then is not primarily
argumentation and coming to conclusion
right discourse and argumentation work
but they're in the service of a bunch of
other practices because the overarching
conception of rationality and I talked
about this with David Chapman I gotta
write some I owe him a couple of letters
so I'm letter that I think that the main
conception there is you know two things
systemic and reliable set of practices
for overcoming self-deception and the
perennial problems that that engenders
and human beings and then systemic and
reliable ways of enhancing religio
enhancing those those aspects of
connection that we talked about earlier
that we now have some scientific
evidence for reliably improve people's
sense of meaning in life and that's
that's the that's the that's what I'm
talking about when I'm talking about
rationality I'm talking about
rationality that ameliorates foolishness
and affords flourishing in systematic
and reliable ways so meditating for me
is as a form of rationality even though
in fact precisely because it is
suppressed in inferential processing it
is doing that in a way that is
appropriate for trying to train in
aspects of insight that are important
for overcoming sure but but you probably
when we think of rationality we think of
I guess to ration is to cut things into
bits and and try to write this it and
then so to ration think so we could sort
of explain what meditation does and have
some kind of rational explanation for
that
whereas what happens in meditation is
not really something that you can
measure or or quantify or put in
scientific you can't you can but see I I
want to challenging you I I don't think
the rat the rat that the ratio and the
rationing is originally to cut out I
think it's it's ratio its proportionate
and what it is it's also many much more
like logistics what is the best way so
like it's a logistical normativity what
is
the best way of disposing of your finite
limited resources as a human being not
about the cutting up of bits of things
and our victims I have to ration this I
know this is what I got for him actually
in McGilchrist his book and his critique
of sort of rationality yeah that was
yeah he was saying you need reason but
not rationality because rationality
means breaking things up into bits and
and and he was sort of he was in the end
of his book he kind of think he says
that we need to restore romanticism in
some kind of a way and you're kind of
saying the opposite thing and I'm
sympathetic to both views because I'm
kind of romantic by Nature
well I'm saying I I think if you like if
you pay attention to let's say and I've
given a talk on this let's say Marcus
Aurelius and the Stoics of course are
advocates of rationality clearly but
what's happening in the practice of
something like the view from above well
you're not making an argument and you're
not an act you're not analyzing and what
are you doing you're doing this
perspectival transformation that is
supposed to radically alter your
salience landscape so that your sense of
self and your sense of identification
are radically transform so you're
capable of aspiring to a different way
of being right and this and this gets me
to a third dimension of the notion of
rationality that's present in the
ancient world that's lost in the modern
and this is this goes to Edna's collards
work which is the aspirational aspect of
rationality we can that's you get that
in a sense of wisdom because but the
Agnes Keller's point is that when we
propose rationality we're actually
proposing to people at aspirational
course because most of us are not very
rational and we're aspiring to become
somebody other than we are to have
salient landscapes other than we have
and have sex of preferences and values
than other than we have yeah it is
aspirational but impossible I mean I I
don't see myself becoming a rational
person I I just I I don't know well let
me let me let me try let me
what what I was trying to do with the
view from above is that is a way in
which you engage in aspirational
rationality that is a way in which you
can use systematic and reliable
practices for bringing about the kinds
of transformation that reduce kinds of
self-deception egocentrism parochialism
and override like these are all
important ways of becoming wiser and so
for me that view from above which is
very similar to some buddhist meditative
practices is a very rational thing to do
not because it's argumentative
rationality okay because it's
aspirational transformational and here's
the bite in coloureds argument if you
don't include aspiration in your
understanding of rationality you are in
a performative contradiction because if
aspiration is not a rational process
then you cannot recommend rationality to
people because when you're recommending
be more rational you're actually
advocating an aspirational
transformation the aspiration to
rationality is actually integral to the
existence of rationality okay I'm not
sure if I'm following all that but it
sounds pretty good well the point is if
if if the what I'm trying to argue if I
was to make it simpler is the process of
becoming more rational has to be part of
our definition of what it is to be
rational and that is aspirational in
nature and so if I'm trying to overcome
self-deception I'm engaged in a
aspirational self transcendence project
it can't be captured by argumentation
because you can't infer your way through
those kinds of transformations but there
are they still have to be central to
rationality that's the point I'm trying
to make yeah yeah so rationality is not
sort of a you know a plot it's not kind
of a linear process it's it's more of
understanding the whole or or
being as look you know it's it's a it's
a I guess yeah it's
I guess Jordan Hall talks about uses
this word coherence oh yeah maybe that's
what that sounds like
when Jordan says coherence it sounds a
bit like what you mean when you say
rational person I think so I mean it was
in a way you know I was talking to
Jordan actually earlier this morning we
were having a conversation around all
this stuff um and and like what he means
by coherence is exactly right to get out
to get something beyond the cultural
cognitive grammar that we have it's a
deeply self-transcendent thing for him
so it's a deeply aspirational thing and
so very very much I think that's the
case III what I'm what the thesis on
arguing against is the this two-stage
reduction reason is argumentation and
argumentation is logic and so being
rational is to be logical I think that
is deeply mistaken I think knowing when
where this is the this is the rathia
knowing when we're in to what degree to
be rare to be logical knowing where when
in to what degree one should argue make
arguments that's the wisdom too isn't it
and understanding the context of thing
yes yeah just having some ideas or yes
exactly that's exactly my point
and that's what I mean about trying to
come up with a conception of rationality
that bridges naturally into the
cultivation of wisdom mm-hmm okay great
okay okay so I guess the next question I
had on my on my list was about
non-theistic religion all right well
after the first question and this one
kind of come so so is that the religion
that's not a religion is that a
non-theistic religion or because non
theistic religions are I guess they
don't have a God principle that they
adhere to but they still have sort of
something like Buddha nature or what
they have same goodness they they
definitely have symbols and I use that
word with a deep kind of meaning they
definitely have symbols for activating
you know accentuating and celebrating
religion that
and and in that in that celebration of
religion in in its acceleration even
there's a sense of the inexhaustible
nosov reality that comes through so I
think all of I think all of the
religions have that and the non theistic
religions have they have non God they
have non personal symbols like likes
things the Dow in Taoism as a
quintessential example right at the Dow
is not a person it's not a god but the
Dow the Dow is you know it's
nevertheless something that in the Delta
H n explicitly says that it puts you
into right into a relationship with the
inexhaustible aspects and it gets you
cultivating wisdom it really enhances
your sense of connectedness of flow
Taoism is the religion of religio and
flow in many ways and so it's a
non-theistic religion I think III for
for me what the not the non-theist is
rejecting the you know presupposition is
an assumption that's shared by opponent
opponent positions right it's different
from just an assumption and so the
non-theistic the non-theist rejects
presuppositions that are accepted by
both the theists and the Atheist that
ultimate reality is right is a being of
some kind the ground of being it seems
to be that non-theistic people talk
about the ground of being yes whereas
theistic people talk about the high the
mighty the supreme being the supreme so
it's the idea it's the idea that being
is ultimately understood as the supreme
being now we have to be very careful
because even within so-called theistic
positions you have mystical traditions
and theologians who challenge that but I
wish that we're talking about sort of
consensus views and so there's the
rejection of the idea that so that the
theist says there is a Supreme Being the
atheist says there isn't but that the
non-theist says that's the best the
wrong way to frame that's the wrong way
to frame sort of ultimate reality the
the the theist and the non-theist both
seem at least
in the Abrahamic traditions were the
ones I'm familiar with to think that the
ultimate relationship to what's sacred
is a relationship of belief it wasn't
always that way but that's what it's
good to be now the non-theist says no
it's not about believing or not
believing this is much more about what
we were talking about earlier am i on a
course of transformation that is making
me wiser right it's tapping into the
procedural the perspectival and the
participatory as just as important as
the propositional so the non theists
also right so it like if there is their
God is this a question like do you
believe in a Supreme Being the
non-theist says well I reject belief as
the central relations the wrong question
or she yeah you're framing the question
the wrong way and then and then the
non-theist also says the question about
and I mean I'm having excellent
discussions with Mary Cohen and JP more
so about this so I don't want to be
dismissive of them but I'm just stating
with the non theists is saying in this
context to answer your question the
non-theist says there are sort of deep
reasons why the question of whether or
not reality ultimate reality is personal
or impersonal is undecidable because the
notion of that reality omit reality is
is similar to us the problem is
similarity is isn't I mean there's the
Goodman critique the similarity of any
two things is ultimately logically
undecidable because the number of
properties that any two things share is
indefinitely large and the number of
properties they don't share is
indefinitely large there's no logical
procedure there is no logical procedure
for deciding similarity there's a deep
argument there so what do we do well we
pick points of comparison that are
particularly relevant to us but then
that then it's not a choice about the
reality of the thing it's a choice about
what's relevant to us
what's symbolically relevant to us so I
get it there for some people personal
symbols are relevant to them and for
other people it's not but the non-theist
says so maybe he feels him and
non-theism can kind of coexist
you know people there's some people who
are more attracted to non-theistic
styles can yeah can can do that and then
other people who are more attracted to
mystic styles can do that as long as
here's another non-theistic point the
non-theist would say as long as you
don't confuse kind of psychological
indispensability with metaphysical
necessity so what's the difference yeah
so somebody may say you know for me
because of my idiosyncratic history or
and/or because of my cultural heritage
the personal symbol works for me and and
work in a deep way not some superficial
utilitarianism
but the 8ly works for me right I it's I
I could I can't do the impersonal I get
that that makes sense to me that that's
even a prediction of sort of relevance
realization theory but to conclude from
that indispensability that that's the
metaphysically true picture of reality
that doesn't follow that just does not
follow so they could exist together but
you see where's the non-theist can say
oh and this is the point this is the
next point the pluralism the non-theist
can say oh I see that I get that can the
feast in good integrity do the same and
say oh I see that I see that it is
equally yeah equally as good I think I
think that the theist gets stuck
somewhere and doesn't go the next step
perhaps that's what we're saying you
know yeah yeah and I think but what I
would say also I do is I think the
Atheist is similarly stuck in rejecting
all of these propositions as somehow the
oh yeah
so the non-theist is trying to say all
of this has been massively Mis framed
for these reasons and several others and
what we need to do is break through that
Mis framing and get back to what's
really at issue here I think which is
the cultivation of wisdom the
enhancement of religio okay I don't mean
to dump a bathtub of concepts on people
I mean I try I'm in III I'm aware of the
fact that I can be sort of oppressive in
the density of my thought but I guess
what I'm trying to do is is more like
more like excessively humble
it's a wonderful feast well okay it's
part of it is appreciate your saying
that part of it is in my mind I have
many arguments and I'm trying to
condense them as much as possible that's
you know and that we can bring into
conversation I would like to point out
that what we just said about the
non-theism also because you did ask me
it happens into this question of a
religion that's not a religion because
there's sort of a presupposition of that
framework as what we're trying to do is
get a set of psycho technologies that is
like they can break out of the axial
grammar and part of that breaking out of
the axial age grammar I think Jordan
high as we understood in Holland I agree
on this is breaking out of the theism
antitheism you know and thinking back
through getting psycho technologies that
have a legitimacy worldview that is not
bound in that stagnant grammar that's
part of what's going on there okay well
there's one more question of all all
this religious stuff that I have and and
that was you know my my friend Alexander
bard who I did I do a podcast with has
some pretty wild ideas and and I thought
that I thought that was and her directly
to of course yeah and and he you know he
he wasn't buying the religion of no
religion at all he was saying we already
have the religion of no religion he's
saying that that's what we have right
now that the religions are weak right
now they're they're not yeah they're
they're they're sort of there and they
need and that actually the the religion
what we actually need to do is go really
back back back back back and find the
primordial religion or find the he calls
it know my dollars you find that do you
know that the your place in in the tribe
in some sense and your your so so yeah I
thought that there's something
interesting about that idea that
religion would be aspirational or
religio you would say yes yeah but would
be something that we don't have or that
we haven't fulfilled and that makes it
aspirational does that make is that well
yeah it's an interesting idea to me so
it's a good point and I take I take
Alexander's
you know this I take Alexander's
critique seriously and and I try to
respond to them and and it's it's
difficult to do that he he is such a I
don't know what I I'm trying to be
complimentary here he like it's you know
helpful Specter had sort of the wall of
sound and music exactly there's so many
ideas coming to you all at once with our
examine our to know where to you know
get up well the first time I talked to
him he he hadn't slept in two days and
and he talked to me for five hours he
did stop once with this wild ideation so
so what I'm saying is I am deeply I'm
deeply concerned that I'm probably going
to misrepresent him as I try to respond
to that critique so I'm acknowledging
that right now so this is what I'm under
start of it I deeply agree with this
critique because I do believe that
religio is inevitable to us and
indispensable to us and I would even
argue metaphysically necessary to us as
cognitive agents so it's deep and
therefore we we are still practically
practicing weak air sacs religions all
over the place because of the fact that
it is it is necessary to our cognitive
being and also to our communal social
being so in the sense I agree with him
that part of the problem is we have and
Chris and I and Philip and I talked
about this in the book right then we
have all these thoughts religions and
all these things that people don't
realize or religion or religion or
something religion that does negative
something living inside of it you know
yeah so I agree with that and and but
that's not what I mean by the religion
that's not religion what I was trying to
do was as I mentioned earlier I was
trying to capture this problem that
we're in that many people reject the
traditional religions right and for them
that's what religion means it means a
traditional religion because of the
problem of its identification with the
Axial Age mythology and they also reject
right the pseudo religious ideologies
the second alternative that's what I was
trying to capture with that and then as
we said also trying to break
free from the stranglehold and I think
Alexander's doing this he seems to be
doing this in his book with his idea of
Cynthia ISM he's trying to break out of
the grammar of atheism in the head and
he's trying to go back to like that the
Silk Route and all the diesel you know
that the whole sort of again all of
these early really early Buddhist and
Zoroastrian eases a rest rien yes sort
of that time when there wasn't these
monolithic religions you know big
monolithic religions where there was a
much much let's say trade and and
discussion between all of these
different yeah schools like let's say
schools of Buddhism or schools of Jerian
is in there you have that even in the
ancient world where you have the ancient
philosophical schools right and and they
exist that's and I and again there's a
point of agreement because I'm trying to
articulate that in terms of an ecology
practices as opposed to trying to argue
for a particular religion with its
monolithic metaphysical worldview right
yeah in there again I think there's a
deep point of agreement um I suppose I
don't want I don't want to just be doing
the move right saying I think
Alexandra's misunderstood me but I'm
trying to say I I'm not just trying to
point out right that we have sort of
like like he says we have these decadent
weakened almost parasitic religions
living in people right now because I
agree with that
and I'm not trying to disagree that we
need something like an ecology practices
and we need to get more back to the
transformational practices
I guess perhaps where there might be
more substantial disagreement is he and
this was in one of your questions he
seems to see this in terms of like that
we need a utopic vision and yeah right
he thinking well he thinks we need to
restore that the grand narrative yes
you know after after the the grand
narrative has sort of died in
post-modernism he sees
we really need a vision or we really
need a story or we really need to be
able to telling tell people the story
otherwise we're just going to continue
deconstructing everything yeah at
absurdum er so again I might I don't
simply reject that claim because I think
there's truth to it I think that the
sense of you know without a vision the
people perish kinda might be a coat from
the Bible I I guess the the the thing
that concerns me is is how we how I'm
trying to be very careful because he has
answers for this but I I'm trying to say
that I don't find these answers yet
convincing it's how do we identify the
utopic vision and how do we disentangle
it from you know the pseudo religious
idea yeah and he acknowledges this he
acknowledges that we've had utopic
visions that have drenched the world in
blood and I and I'm I'm very hesitant
about that as the way of trying to
create of whatever what do we watch we
call it an encouraging vision for people
I agree that we need to be you're
worried that we get we'll get hooked on
some pseudo religious ideology again and
yes don't go through the same you know
parasitical you know thing right
definitely
so what I what I've been trying to
explore and it's right and this is a
partial response to Alexander I think is
our because I take seriously what he
said but but can we can we create is
their way of constructing not just
deconstructing any and let's let's be
clear about this this isn't this can't
be purely theoretical construction is
their way of constructing you know
ecologies of practices communities of
practices networks of communities I mean
this is how the religions actually
became what they did they didn't start
out they grew this way as communities of
practices that network together and then
increasingly right
I'm seriously engaged with that project
I'm working with people and my point and
I tweet about people who are doing this
and I engage like and you know I'm
working with Chris with that great with
that and all of this like that's that's
for me is okay if we're talking about
vision for me it's like okay what what
are the design and this is we saw this
with what are the design features how do
we get the architecture of getting that
will coordinate this bottom-up process
that's already happening yeah right with
the religion that is not a religion
we're not trying to found anything
there's all of this is happening right
now there's all these new emergent
psycho technologies all these new
emerging communities all this nascent
networking that's going on let's try and
bring some reflective design and
architecture to this so can we afford it
as much as possible yeah so I have
Alexander's voice in my head because I
know it's critique of that as well and
his critique is that it's it's it's
you're building the container that
there's an obsession with the container
there's an obsession with etiquette
there's a session with making sure that
we you know have good conversations and
this is this kind of thing but then
again he's always saying we need this
fly like vision where we can like know
yeah so we need to balance like the
matriarchal which is the container with
the paper with with a positive
patriarchal not a tyrannical picture
which is which is the sort of the
straight-ahead visionary sort of you
know
yeah principle yeah and I want to be
fair to Alexander in that like he died I
mentioned it he all he clearly has a
response to me when I worry about you
know you know the the the the sort of
evil utopia is the dystopia is that
we've continually fallen into I'm not as
convinced about the psychoanalytic
terminology is helping given me a clear
path for doing that is it just a
container is it I mean in just a
container the container is not important
it's it's it's vitally important but I
Figgy say it's an imbalance or I mean
that's what he's always saying and no I
get that
and I get that he's very charitable
about it he says that I should keep
doing what I'm doing it he should be
doing what he's doing and I want to
acknowledge that I want to acknowledge
all of that all of that is going on
because that is important but that goes
to the point I'm trying to make I mean
what makes I mean what makes people
think their lives are more meaningful
connections to other people right a
sense that they're connected to reality
a sense that they have sort of
autonomous competence they're connected
to them you know they matter they have a
sense of connect and and purpose is one
of the four factors but you can't reduce
meaning in life to purpose and the
evidence is now coming out that purpose
isn't as important as we thought it is
Boston culture may be over emphasizing
purpose mattering being in a sense of
deep connection to what's most real and
right and a sense of being in in
developmental caring with other these
seem to be much more important to people
sense of meaning in life yeah and like
and if that's why all of a sudden I'm
thinking of Jordan Peterson now when
you're talking about that and I'm
thinking that it was like a balance to
Jordan Peterson's view you know because
it's not always about purpose and
meaning and getting you know and that
sort of thing and having an aim and
having a direction and you know that's
not it's that's that's that's his view
and you're sort of your get your giving
this other perspective well I'm trying
to say that the evidence is emerging and
is pretty good evidence that it's
reducing meaning in life to purpose is
just I think incorrect that's that's and
that there's other factors this sense of
mattering and their sense of being
connected to something larger than
yourself the sense of right the the
sense of participating in agape right oh
you know all these things all matter and
they there's some evidence that these
that they matter more than purpose and
that's why I try to argue for that this
is a feminine again because the word
matter is it is not related to the word
mother well it can be
but I'm not quite sure what I'm sorry
III know I I'm I'm just I'm inundated by
both of your points of view and I'm
appreciative of both of them I'm not
trying to argue one and and and that and
I don't want to I don't want to box you
in because of that like I'm trying but I
am trying to articulate why I think I'm
not just talking about the container
okay I think I think the content is
meaning in life and deeply because I
don't know what else the content would
be if we're if there's live Alexander
will allow me and I'm not using this in
a mocking tone but if it isn't the
phallic vision to get me a place where I
have one meaning I mean if it's not that
what is it what like what is it for
right it certainly that's what Jordan
Peterson thinks that the colic vision is
about making your life more meaningful
so let's actually ask this question we
can ask it scientifically we're doing it
what are the things that actually make
our life more isodd more meaning in life
aya would argue that that's that's the
that's a lot of content and the
container that I'm building is actually
directed towards a lot of that content
okay what is the meaning like can you
say that in a very succinctly like what
would you say like how with your
scientific understanding what is meaning
in life yeah I think meaning in life is
to have these four factors they don't
and this is the variation this is the
individual difference you don't have to
have like it's not like everybody has to
have all all four factors equally you
can have you can be you can have sort of
less of one factor and compensative with
it by the others so there's much more
pluralism here also well so now that if
you allow me that if that sort of
understood that it's not a simple sort
of feature list
it's a dynamical system yeah within that
dynamical system meaning in life is a
sense of connectedness to what's real
what's significant it's somehow bigger
than you a sense of mattering to others
and to reality a sense of right being
cared for by others that other people
and these this is in a sense of
relationships that have a
developmental import for you and then a
sense of purpose a sense that there is
some overarching goal that all of your
other goals are subservient to which is
I think what Alexander mean by the
phallic vision and I think meaning in
life is to have all of that Nikki Hey
would you would you agree that that sort
of thing is has been lost like let's say
in the modern modern world I think
deeply so yeah I mean it's it's not it's
it's lost in the sense that our that
we're not in touch with it and we don't
have religio about it but like we don't
we can't have a way to channel a tear or
to write to activate it and accelerate
it and celebrate it and excited right
yeah so it becomes pathological because
of that yes and part of the reason for
that is that a lot of these
relationships that I've been talking
about this connectedness to yourself to
others to reality right there that that
connectedness is not largely held by our
proposition alone knowing it's held by
our procedural skills it's it's held by
our perspectival salient landscape it's
held by our participatory
identifications
it's how about it's it's and to degree
to which we are suffering from sort of a
propositional tyranny
we have disconnected ourselves very
fundamentally right and existentially in
an embodied way from the machinery of
that connectedness and therefore we
suffer very deeply and I that's why I
don't think ideological solutions are
because ideologies just move
propositions around right now
propositional theory is relevant because
the propositional theory can help you
right we're doing it right now can help
me get back in touch with these forms of
knowing that deeply connect us but the
degree to which we are just again this
goes back to the non-theism degree to
which we're just asserting beliefs and
somehow the solution to meaning your
life I think is true and emphatically
and not just sexually existentially miss
frame how we are trying to get more
meaning in life and boy do we need
meaning a month we real
okay great great
this brought me to like the last
question I had in my list of questions
and and you know your series is called
awakening to the meaning crisis or
weakened from
awake excuse me awakening from the
meaning crisis so I was thinking yes
okay so we awaken from the meaning
crisis well that's that's a big ask but
let's say we understand the meaning
crisis and we've somewhat awakened from
it what's the next step what do we do
when when we understand like that's why
I'm trying to have this that's why I'm
trying to push this nicely constructive
vision like what would what would be
yeah you know I love the circling stuff
is it's great it's beautiful and my only
fear is that you could do these sort of
things forever you know like they do in
epsilon these kind of activity is where
you get together and usually you know
discuss where you're at and you know but
then there's this so I was thinking the
vision I had was that there's a circle
and then there also has to be again a
line and this goes to current work that
I'm doing with Chris and also to you
know with guys head start because you
know he wants to he wants to create what
he calls circling 2.0 right and and the
work I'm doing with Jordan and Jordan I
were talking about again Jordan Hall
about this now I mean part of it is this
you know this idea about dialectic and
about the idea of
trying to come up with a meta psycho
technology that will better fit us so we
can access it and activate it better
collect the collective intelligence of
distributed cognition and like we talked
earlier Ratchet it up into distributed
rationality Ratchet it up into
distributed collective wisdom so that we
can Shepherd ecologies of practices so
that we can then go on enhancing religio
in a much more systematic reliable and
scalable fashion and then what that what
does that mean right I don't know what
that means what it will look like on the
other side I don't know what the
coherence world looks like and this is
where Alexander is going to be angry
with me right you say you'd be saying
you're not giving us enough we need to
know like yeah we need to know like
where the promised land is you know and
we need to we need to know and I agree
with that
I mean I'm also I guess I would ask
Alexander to acknowledge that humans
have a proclivity to jumping to
conclusions and not paying enough
attention to how well they have
formulated their problems and that is
one of our deep resetting and pervasive
sins and so I'm very aware of that and
so that's why I'm very hesitant about
trying to leap beyond I do think the the
beginning of the answer it goes back to
the point I'm making with I made earlier
with you sorry the point I'm making goes
back to a point I made earlier with you
about being in being in dialogue and
hopefully being able to bring dialectic
into this into the dialogue with these
people who are creating these
communities in the network like they're
I have to be careful here there is a
real potential notice both words both
real and potential that a new culture is
being created a new way of human beings
being that seems to be clear to me it
just seems yet be happening right right
man yeah go ahead please no no I mean I
just want to say yes that it seems to be
happening just something is happening
right
and so my hope is that by getting a
dialectic which is both as you said that
the circling this way and also the
self-transcending upward right because
that was both but we we can we can use
the ancient template of dialectic
platonic dialectic and bring it into
these new emerging practices of
connecting and dialoguing and community
making because that's what it did in the
ancient world let's use it as a template
we're not a religion I'm not nostalgic
let's use it as a template transfer and
adapt it give a guidance for how we talk
connect how we do the things that build
culture better so that we can perhaps
build you know I like what Steven
Bachelor calls it a culture of awakening
so that we can move to a place where and
we've had this in our past so this is
not some where their context of the
world is waking us up it's not putting
us to sleep or drugging yes turning us
into zombies and and we're where the
where wisdom and a meaningful life well
we're a good life is a meaningful life
not just a a comfortable or pleasurable
life where wisdom and a meaningful life
are for grounded in what the culture is
oriented around because our culture is
not oriented towards that so part of
what that would happen after we awaken
is that process of getting the meta
psycho technology getting the dialectic
using that hopefully hopefully helping
facilitate the process of the emerging
culture and oriented towards a culture
focused on wisdom and meaning that's
what I would like to see if you know it
is that utopic maybe but I'm really
trying to keep the balance of my
cognition towards not leaping and
deforming the problem really really well
well that's why yeah mmm great well as
you were speaking excuse me I was
thinking you know this makes sense
and I was also thinking about about
where let's say mythopoetic sand art and
music and and all of these things are
fit into all this because I find that a
lot of the discussion out there is very
heady I'm not accusing you of that I
think I think you're also very warm and
your expression I and also Kristoff to
me seems like an amazing poet this guy I
love the way he uses yeah I love though
yeah i love the way i love the way he
uses language and speaks i think yeah
he's kind of a poet or something and you
know he he wants so take this with a
grain of salt but he one sort of said
you know you're sort of socrates to me
but uh and then uh and I said well Devon
Socrates or Plato because you hear his
gift work with Chris not only because
he's a dear a deep friend and I think so
highly of him as a person but one of the
reasons I work with Chris is precisely
to get this balance you're talking about
yeah right artistry I was wondering
about that yeah yeah I wanted to ask
that question actually uh it's like it
seems that you're just you're just so
you know high-speed conceptual you know
powerful in that way and and and and he
seems to have almost this poetic
feminine quality or something I don't
know what to call her
he he his he once described it this way
he says you know he's he's he said you
know John builds the universe but then I
furnish it okay right and there's a lot
in there like like what many things that
chris says there's so much in there you
know that he his his language isn't only
lyrical it's it's rich right I can he he
the you know the finding the right word
and finding the right phrase isn't just
a matter you know sort of its lyrical
sounding if it's also you know
he finds the nexus point in an epistemic
web and he finds but if I if I make this
point vibrate that will make everything
else comprehensible for everybody and he
just he just does that yes he plucks the
string and everything vibrates I
struggled to make arguments he just goes
ding and yeah right well it's my
experience with of talking to him was
really wonderful because well you know
in my 20s and 30s I was a musician and I
I wrote poetry and I was in the art
world and all I cared about really was
that I I wasn't so empirical or logical
I wasn't I was I read a lot but you know
I was just in a in a foolish sort of way
and and and when I started talking to
him I felt right at home I felt like
okay this is like suddenly a person that
I could speak this language to and that
this kind of person is rare that you
don't find people like that that you can
actually communicate in that way with so
so I just was just such a breath of
fresh air and and so I mean we he and I
I mean I have other great partnerships
the partnership I had with Leo Ferraro
was actually also a fantastic
partnership but the partnership I have
with Chris it's we exemplify we
exemplify dialogo stand dialectic we
together produce something that neither
one of us is capable on our own and and
and that that if you'll allow me
you know the mixture of argumentation
and artistry both these terms are too
simple and too reductive but I'm using
the digestion sure that that mixture is
exactly what is needed for as you said
for responding to the meeting crisis I
wrote down I wrote collaboration as a
remedy to the to the meeting crisis yes
and maybe this idea of individual
authorship which is important perhaps
and but but also that it seems to me
that that there's something more
possible in that kind of relationship
that you're doing then then then just
the one guy or whatever I have it seems
to be an amazing way to work and I wish
it would work that way or I
I could work that way with the people in
collaborating with more oh yeah I'm
doing that more and more but but I have
never published a single work where I am
the single author I can't think of it I
just I in that sense I'm deeply platonic
deeply Socratic that's great yeah the
dialogic thought is an ultimately
dialectical thinking and dialectical
interaction because it's more than just
thinking it's just so much more powerful
that's what I mean about can we access
distributed cognition and can we get it
so that it is ratcheting up into
distributed rationality distributed
wisdom I mean can we take distributed
intelligence and get it up there into
into distribute well clearly that it has
been my personal experience regularly
and reliably that that's the case that's
possible so I believe it's possible
because I know it's possible in my own
case and then and and like I said my
best work is done with others yeah and
so I think if we could get past sort of
the commitment to sort of the individual
author and the individual Authority
because those two are deeply related
then I think that would be a very
important thing so I think you're right
to put your finger on the fact that for
me
collaboration exemplifies a lot of what
I'm talking about it is it is an
exemplification of a lot of what I'm
trying to argue for mm-hmm yeah
the other thing I wrote down as also you
had this wonderful discussion with ghee
Christophe in Jordan and oh yeah as I
was watching that I was thinking there's
something more going on here than just
intellectual banter there's or something
that is very it's like it's like a rare
thing to just observe like that right
well for me into what happened what
we've done two of those now yeah oh it's
actually pronounced God by the way
excuse me
and that's what I mean what a guy it
wants because guys guys circling
practice is not guys circlings practice
is deeply deeply motivated and informed
and reference to he's attempting to try
and figure out how to translate
Heidegger into authentic dialogue that's
what he's trying to do so and so guy is
in there he and he what he's trying to
do and if that's what he's doing it in a
participatory fashion it's can we bring
in the circling but can we integrate it
with argumentation can we integrate it
with conceptualization can we constantly
move between theory and theoria that's
what he's doing and and what we're
trying to do is we're trying to
exemplify dialectic as something beyond
just conversation and you know for me
andrew both both those times especially
the second one i texted chris later and
i said I felt like I was in a platonic
dialogue like one of Plato's texts I've
never had that experience or that's very
interesting yeah and I imagine that
that's the way people used to
communicate in in olden times right when
you would you know I just had this
vision I'm sort of sitting around and
like I don't know people trying to make
decisions and they would sit together
and try to make decision it wouldn't be
just like like a parliament where this
is you know if this proposition versus
this proposition and we debate it would
be like you would wait until your heart
speaks in some kind of a way and and
then there would be you know it wouldn't
be it wouldn't have this intense level
of antagonism and competition that we we
kind of always are you know subject to
or have to live put on or you know this
kind of protectiveness or mmm Plato
talks about that he distinguishes
between finals like Sophia the pursuit
of wisdom and fondle and IKEA the
pursuit of victory and part of what
we've done is is we've gotten we've
become so immersed and overwhelmed with
adversarial process and we've lost a
point upon the idea of a point of
processing is a system is
self-correcting
all like your eyes
like yeah yeah yeah we're laxity riser
though mm-hmm or or the point of
processing between your parasympathetic
and your sympathetic nervous system to
constantly right recalibrate your level
of physiological arousal right and so
what do you see an opponent processing
is it is a system that is dynamically
continually self-corrective and the
opponents are always ultimately
committed to a shared process of the
health of the system and that was what
democracy was sort of supposed to be but
what's happening I think and this is an
ideal I automatically got from Lea
Ferrara
right is that notion of opponent
processing in which the other guy by the
other side the other person I should
have just said the other guy the other
person right is opposed opposing me but
they're probably helping me to
self-correct and we're working together
in this fashion of self-corrected to
maintain democracy to maintain the
process of democracy that kind of model
has disappeared and we've replaced it
with this adversarial winner-take-all it
did nothing else matters yeah right well
there could be a kind of positive
antagonism where you're challenging
somebody like in a wrestling match or
something you're wrestling with ideas
and that's positive right but but it's
the it's the it's the I guess the
zero-sum game kind of right think about
guard imitation
and the commitment to sportsmanship the
idea right is I can be in a good match
when I lose because my opponent self it
helps me to correct my my wrestling
right so I should be grateful I should
be respectful and grateful even when I
lose because it can be a good match
because winning isn't what I'm
ultimately here for I'm ultimately here
for it to become a better wrestler and
my opponent is helping me do that and so
I should express gratitude I should
express respect and I should right and
so because we're both we share both if
we're sports fed right or sports person
we share a commitment to becoming better
to accelerating as wrestlers and we can
both help each other in that and you
know even in even in that positive
antagonism there is the sense that my
opponent is one of the most powerful
ways for helping me self correct and
both of us are committed to the process
of human improvement through wrestling
through this particular sport I think
sport has lost a lot of this ethos too
it's become very much the
winner-take-all uh model and it's just
about winning about competition and you
know it would win winning becomes
paramount and with the process you don't
care about the process then then why not
cheat yeah then why not you I feel it's
also just the way we commit the way the
communication level you get on on
Twitter or Facebook is like that it's
it's it's just it's very subtle maybe
but it's it's but it but it's like it's
not we're not helping each other
oh no we're trying to bring each other
we're trying to pull each other down or
something on some level we're trying and
we're spreading our darkness around her
you know well I think this goes back to
a point we made earlier think about how
truncated and isolated and restricted to
purely propositional knowing you are
with things like Twitter and Facebook
right exactly yeah yeah I mean I guess
this is a video so we could see each
other's face and here
voices and that adds a whole other
dimension to it then it would be if it
was just you know text and and what
we're doing often is we are coordinating
our salience landscapes we're sort of
coordinating at least conceptually right
what we're paying attention to and what
we're for grounding and back rounding
and we're doing this in a cooperative
you know sometimes we're disagreeing but
nevertheless we're doing it at a
cooperative Mayor's you know can we get
alignment to our salience landscape and
we're also bringing in our particular
existential mode where we're talking
about like where we're bringing
ourselves as identities also into the
discussion it's not just propositions
that's going on here for example you
asked me you know about you know you
know the way collaboration with Chris
reaches the into how I work and who I am
that's Oh I mean I'm I I'm not I hope
I'm not naive I don't I don't I don't
think that even like I think a lot of
YouTube right can think it could be
disastrous for people mm-hmm sure but
the series and the and one of the gifts
the series has given me is getting to
meet and to deeply dialogue with people
like yourself yeah
but the series and the and the dialogues
and and the people I've met in the
communities I've met they've been deeply
encouraging to me that there is a real
potential here in this medium and in the
community and in the people that are and
the competence and the commitment that
people are bringing to these communities
there is a real potential here there is
a real potential and it's already being
actualized and I want to do more to
actualize that but then huh great
yeah yeah me too you know you know I was
right I'm working a little bit with
rebel wisdom and writing an article for
them and it's it seems to be that I'm I
have two lives now yeah there's my
there's my you know my job you know
and there's my which I do for money
because I have to and because I need to
survive uh-huh and then there's the
things I really care about it it's
almost like the things I really care
about are sort of taking over the the
stuff that is is is more let's say you
know nitty gritty ER that of which is
also important I guess in life but it's
also where I hope I'm not being naive or
have illusions I understand and I
appreciate in all the senses of that
word that I I've been very lucky
position that my profession and my
vocation are deeply interpenetrating
with each other and and I understand
that that can't be the case for many
people I get that and so I I hope that
if at times I'm presumptuous because I'm
lucky that people point that out to me
because I would be helpful I would be
very helpful poppy to self-correct
on that point because I'm aware of the
fact then I the thing that calls to me
my vocation and the thing I get to do
for money that they're deeply
interpenetrating and a deeply satisfying
way for me and but you must have this
one pointed you know desire and you must
have had it for a long time I mean I I
can't imagine you know how much you read
and how much or how much where I got the
amount of work to do so so I'm sure it's
it's it's it's merited I mean well thank
you for saying that I've worked very
hard and very long and I only recently
got tenure after being at the University
for 25 years so it was a long hard Wow
hard hard work and I and I did have to
do a lot of what you said so thank you
for saying that nevertheless the fact
yes I did work hard for it and I think
in that sense it's deserved but I do
want to always be sensitive to the fact
that you know people don't have my
temperament a lot of people might not
know not might not have my bent for
abstract theoretical thought or the the
kind of need for cognition that I have
and that doesn't mean that they
shouldn't be afforded good and reliable
ways of pursuing wisdom and meaning in
life and so again I want to be sensitive
to to that and I want my hope is it in
and I hope I'm not boxing you into an
inappropriate category my hope is it
being in discussion with non academics
like you helps to address that issue I
just brought up it helps bridge between
the very lucky life that I have and the
lives that many people don't have such
that what I'm saying can still be
valuable to people who don't have the
kind of lucky situation I have with it
but nevertheless like all of us need to
cultivate wisdom and meaning in life
yeah oh that's that's great that's a
very generous and you know gracious
attitude it's very touching to hear you
say that you know well thank you for
saying that it but but it sincerely
meant an antenna
these have all been great questions I'm
open to more questions if you have any
more that you'd like to I have
it's funny because I've been going
through the minute and I think I've
almost covered all of them on my list I
have there's more of course I have you
know I've got more questions for you one
of the things is today I was interesting
I was on Facebook and and I posted my
article which was I wrote about your
series about the religion of no religion
and somebody asks the question is saying
what what are you doing differently then
let's say other people like that we're
doing it Esalen and fritz perls and
joseph campbell and all these people
that were trying to kind of create a an
ecology of psycho decide you know an
ecology of practices develop psycho
technologies create a religion that was
not a religion what's your particular
let's say I don't mean to say what are
you doing Mike in any kind of like oh
this is the new thing but what is your
if you think your particular angle is
your particular let's say thing thing
that you have to give to this oh it's a
couple things here I don't know all the
people you were referring to there so
I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm gonna use the
one that I have somewhat familiarity
with which is Joseph Campbell as my as
my point of comparison so if you'll
allow me to use him as a sort of an
exemplary fashion it may be young via
Joseph Campbell and maybe the other
maybe also that that would be but
there's a bit of a contrast with Jordan
Peterson I think young gave us a set of
valuable psycho technologies and I did
deep training in those I've been through
Jungian therapy I went through work like
I've done a lot I'm not claiming to be a
clinical psychologist I am NOT claiming
that but I have a you know and I do
practice some of these psycho
technologies I've done the same thing 25
years of Metta the Pastner Tai Chi Chuan
like so I have deeply learned a lot of
these psycho technologies I have a long
deep philosophical trend a training in
order also to work with right the
philosophical world
use the wisdom traditions surrounding
all of these psycho technologies and
then I have training as a cognitive
scientist that I can bear on all of
these things and sorry this was a
tremendously self-referential question
so it sounds like I'm being
self-promotional right now and I
apologize for that but I'm trying to
answer your question right yeah no I
didn't want to put you in a position of
having to sell yourself III just wanted
to know what is like because it seems to
me that that that there's what whatever
was going on in the 70s and 80s and you
know what people were interested in had
a similarity to what you're doing now
does it does but but and and it was kind
of revolutionary and it kind of exploded
and it kind of deflated again yes and
and that that there's a kind of a new
approach to these things that is
emerging and you're kind of at the
forefront of that or one of the major
dollars in that so so so so I want to
know what's different about it so yeah
what these new movements yeah you know a
deep learning of all the kinds of
knowing of these psycho technologies and
these practices in the tradition a deep
training in you know three kinds of
philosophy you know analytic philosophy
continental philosophy and we don't have
a good adjective for it anymore but what
used to be called Eastern philosophy and
all of those right and you know and also
important you know like the Kyoto School
Misha Thani had a profound impact on me
for example and then like I said and
also you know like I said you got my
next question for you yeah but but being
able to bring what I think is
cutting-edge cognitive science into
relationship with all of that this is
not a good enough adjectives with all of
that practical knowledge all that
practical knowing and bring it into a
deep a deep dialogue I think that's what
is adding depth so well I again I'm very
hesitant about hubris here but while I
acknowledges the similarities are
hoping that that training that right and
that skillset allowed me to bring a
depth to this that will help give it a
kind of longevity that that stuff in the
70s didn't have great great okay so I
also want to ask you just a little bit
about well when you didn't mentioned it
was the philosophy shoot any or tiny he
wrote one of the great books on the
relationship between what I he would
call them I think in given our
discussion we could call sort of
religious transformation and the
response to nihilism part of his
argument was the West is incapable of
understanding to nihilism because the
West gives a gives an undefended
priority to being the being anonymous
yeah and and and and it's not just the
conceptual issues we don't have what I
would call psycho technologies of
strength of transformation and self
transcendence that actually afford that
profound you know aspect change in a
perspectival knowing in our
participatory identification so that we
can go from just saying emptiness to
experiencing emptiness as the fount the
sacred fount positive principle rather
than a negative principle or privation
yes exactly so that but we need both a
conceptual change and a psycho
technological change and if you allow me
the way ink should philosophy kept those
two together we need a philosophical
transformation in order to address the
problem now isn't that so religion and
nothing that is a profound book so
emptiness in the Buddhist sense can
address this this issue of nihilism I
think so Shin Yatta Yatta I'm but I
think there are deep and I mean deep and
I mean procedurally prospectively
participatory deep similarities not
identities but similarities between the
Neoplatonic notion of the one that was
notion of the I know I follow this
actually I'm not a perennial list what
I've what I'm saying is
that these things have symbolic
functional similarities in the way in
which they can engender the
transformation the aspect shift that
deep and profound and comprehensive
aspect shift that is needed for
addressing nihilism you get that I think
in the Neoplatonic aspiration to the one
in the taoist flow residence with the
dow right so I think that yes I think
Shunyata is is symbolically powerful but
I think there are equally powerful
symbols yes yes Connie would say that
too and I think you even get something
similar in even in Western theology
I think Tillich's God beyond the God of
theism also ultimately a kind of
non-theism it's kind of Gnostic
non-theism I think is also because his
great book the courage to be is how do
we bring about a conceptual and
existential transformation so we deal
with not meeting crisis that was the
courage to be and you know the ultimate
proposal is the God beyond the god of
theism and so he also I think even
within sort of classical Western
Protestant theology you have people
trying to create again and until it
would be happy with this word a symbol
that affords the rigorous negative
theology as well to had some of that in
it yes I'm not an expert I'm a
pseudo-dionysius and that very much well
you thing with I mean the thing with
pseudo-dionysius and I think also with
Tillich but with pseudo-dionysius and
especially with era Jena is you actually
what actually is at work is is is a
dialectic in that you're moving between
you're moving between a negative sort of
like you've called it a negative
theology where you know you're trying to
shut down all the ways in which you are
trapped in conceptualization and
categorize a
that's always a dialectic with with the
with the it right with the insights you
have in Newry conceptualizations so the
idea is that's the catafalque right what
is one of the two names in scatter panic
and I can't remember the two names I Wis
Johnathan Podge over here you'd be able
to correct me on this but what you're
constantly do is you're you're
constantly saying and on saying and the
answer is neither in the saying nor the
unsay it's constantly in in what I talk
about right are talking about this
constant evolution of what I would say
is your relevance realization machinery
that the constant evolution of your
religio that's where the answer is to be
mmm-hmm that's that's a dynamic sort of
unending process yes sort of you know
potential you know coming in in and out
of existence rather than some sort of
concrete dogmatic yeah superstructure
yes I think right the idea that that
sacredness is ultimately in a
completable finishable
right sort of absolute thing and rather
that sacredness is you know strangles
notion if the finite always longing for
the infinite yeah we we only experience
the sacredness in the transcendence went
well right right and whenever we try and
stabilize it or finish it right and this
is it then we actually lose the moment
of sacredness right so they had this
notion I talked about in the series of
an effect ASIS that it with that we're
not trying to come to rest or completion
in God right what we're trying to do is
God is the affordance of our continual
self transcendence which is a very
different notion and you see that in I
believe it's it starts with Gregory of
and then you see it a bit in Maximus and
you especially see it in the other Gina
mm-hmm
near the earth direction or the rock
tradition has kept its connections to
the platonic and neo platonic roots much
more alive than in Dedham yeah well it's
why it's if it feels more attracted to
me oh yeah in Christianity because I
guess because they also work with
symbols right and very much as a
practitioner of lejiana we it's very
much a symbolic path and we work we work
with symbols and we work with you know
Mondelez and and think every month right
right and so so I totally agree I mean
you you might want to talk to Jonathan
pazzo at some point because yeah I've
talked to him a little bit I I i I'd
like to talk I'd love to talk to him one
day actually I really enjoy his stuff
you know the symbolic world and his work
on symbolism who just speaks very deeply
to what you just mentioned like his
drawing again from the eastern orthodoxy
is that tradition of deeply
understanding how powerful you know this
symbolic world is that yeah that's
that's the whole point and and we're
we're kind of symbolically illiterate in
the modern world and in a sense right
and there's all these things going on
which we don't know how to read because
we're we're four too much on the surface
or a noisy surface of reality or
something yeah I mean the I think that I
mean to say something a little bit
slogan istic but I think you know
ultimately the relationship between the
surface and the depths it's going to
require symbols I mean because you
you're your if if what we're talking
about is if we're moving if we're trying
to get transcendence we're always moving
from one friend to a more encompassing
frame and so we need something that has
an on logical identity it has it has to
it has to have one kind of identity
inside our frame and then it has to have
another kind of identity that takes us
beyond our frame or it's not gonna
transfer a mus in any way and symbols
joining together right symbol on that's
it's inherently symbolic I think
we can't do without symbols if it goes
back to the point earlier about you know
the aspirational rationality is going to
be bound up with symbols in powerful
ways mm-hmm
and I think Jonathan's work just I mean
Jonathan's brilliant Jonathan Pardo his
bro he's very brilliant yeah and and and
and I mean I like Jonathan a lot I mean
we disagree but but I like I trust being
in dialogue with them because that
brilliance the I don't get any sense of
hubris from that man at all there's no
right there's no arrogance to it there's
just a tremendous there's just you know
infectious enthusiasm and a wanting to
share and I wanted to lift keep other
people up by basically you know he's
kind of like one of those people when
you travel to a strength when you're a
stranger in a strange land and you get
the guide that takes you into the
culture of that world then Jonathan is
like that he's he's that he's that he's
a wonderful guy that is taking you into
so that you can come to live within the
symbolic world and live from its power
and he does that and it seems natural to
him it yeah it just wonderful yeah it is
very he he does he does describe the
world of sin living symbolism and in a
way that this is very hospitable and
easy easy to enter in and kind of and
and and and it's full of this sort of
insight which gonna I read is actually I
read his brothers book too which is very
you should read it it's a really
beautiful little book it blew me away
it's it's very clearly written and it's
an amazing book I can see that they
probably have some kind of symbiotic
relationship which he sort of maybe the
more abstract guy and he's the more
communicator something like that perhaps
perhaps
well I I didn't get much sleep last
night and I I wasn't I was I was and and
I didn't know if my brain could handle
all of this today but it's been it's
been great yeah I I've really thoroughly
enjoyed it I'd be happy to do this again
with you at some point in the future and
reviewed like I would absolutely love to
yeah yeah that'd be great okay great I
really appreciate that I mean I like
what Sevilla King talks about she talks
about she has the the channel of quality
existence very interesting stuff and she
talks about this corner of the internet
yeah it's a pretty big corner because I
think rebel wisdom is is an integral
part of this corner of the internet but
I know what she needs there's there's
this place where there's this forming
community of people who want to enter
into these kinds of discussions and
really want to you know not just talk
but you know afford you know practices
and new ways of life for for addressing
what's happening to us collectively and
individually right now and and and I
mean I think that I guess what I'm
saying is I feel like you belong very
very well within this this place of the
internet because I said sometimes you
feel like you're not quite you didn't
quite have a place where you belong it's
I've heard you talk I think with Chris
about that sort of sense and I think you
want I think you really belong I belong
here oh then that's that's that like
that's good to hear thank you yeah well
I I know that when I started doing this
kind of thing it felt very strange like
you know putting your earphones on
talking on and I I you you said that you
were socially phobic and I think I have
a little bit of that too but I also
think there's something about me that
really wants to like get something out
there they're sort of you know so so so
so I do these kind of things with fear
and trepidation and resistance and
terror and all that but but but it's
usually worth worthwhile
III know this conversation this feels to
me extraordinarily worthwhile so so
me too I thank you for it let's so yeah
and I thank you yeah that's maybe that's
where maybe that's where we could end
huh I think so this feels like a good
place for it to come to an end